welcome back to AP US History in under 3
minutes no time for intros let's get
into it topic 3.2 is on the French and
Indian War also known as the Seven Years
War so to start this one off I'm going
to ask a question what was the first
world war you might say well World War I
because it has a one in it some
historians however would argue the S
Years War was the first world war
because there was involvement from
countries all over the world the fact is
this war is complex and was fought in
many theaters but for AP US History we
will only examine the US side of things
this War started because of territorial
disputes particularly in the Ohio River
Valley and mostly in the new world
between the British and the French
British peoples were moving to the
colonies in massive numbers and this
forced the British to expand threatening
French Indian trade networks and
American Indian autonomy but let's be
real this might be the official cause of
the war but Britain and France had had
beef before this war and this was kind
of the chance for them to settle that
beef the French and British had allied
with many native tribes and so Colony
armies combined with Native Americans
would fight in this war the war started
with a battle of the famous Fort
Necessity which the British lost notice
the number of troops on both side of
this battle it's very small the only
thing you should maybe know about this
battle is it featured the general of
George Washington in the early half of
this war it's fair to say that the
British were heavily losing the French
just kept winning each battle and the
British were just sleepy I mean take a
look at the Battle of mangila the French
had around 400 troops and the British
had, 1300 despite having three times the
Manpower Britain still lost this battle
because of their conventional line
infantry tactics as as opposed to the
French and Indian's Guerilla Warfare
tactics however the tide turned after
1758 as Britain leveraged its Superior
Naval power and resources to gain the
upper hand key victories at Quebec and
Montreal in 1759 and 1760 were crucial
to their successes and finally in 1763
with the signing of the Treaty of Paris
the war ended by this point in the war
there was so many more forces than the
beginning there are two big outcomes of
this war that you should know first the
French lost almost all of their
territorial claims in the Americas and
they were split up amongst the British
and the Spanish the second is that this
war made both Britain and France heavily
broke for Britain this resulted in the
imposition of new taxes on the American
colonies but I get ahead of myself in
France the financial crisis caused by
the war was one of the factors that led
to the French Revolution after the
British Victory Imperial officials
attempted to prevent colonists from
moving Westward and this generated
Colonial opposition while native groups
sought to both continue trading with
Europeans and resist the encroachments
of colonists on tribal lands on the
screen now are AP style questions for
this topic pause
now I'll put the answers on the screen
now see you in the next one